Nine hundred years ago...?
أقلت منذ 900 عام؟
What are you talking about?!
ماذا تقصد بحديثك؟
Are you saying a futuristic city like this existed back then, too?!
أتقصد أن مدينة مستقبلية كهذه كانت موجودة منذ سنواتٍ عدةٍ خلت؟
It's just a theory.
إنها مجرد فرضية
There was a man who once risked his life for archaeology...
...رجلٌ خاطر بحياته لحفظ علم الآثار
to shed light on that ancient kingdom.
سلط الضوء على مملكة قديمة بعينها...
And... machinery excavated from a particular site dates back to that kingdom's reign.
ثم زامن تاريخ صناعة آلة -اُكتشفت بأحد مواقع التنقيب- مع تلك المملكة
That machine was built during the Void Century?!
هل صُنعت تلك الآلة خلال القرن الفارغ؟
How much do you know, exactly?
ما معلوماتكِ عنه؟
Robin! You know about this?!
هل تعرفين عنه شيئًا يا روبين؟
I'm sure it's painful to remember...
،لا أحسبنكِ تريدين إعادة التفكير في الماضي
but twenty-two years ago, your home, Ohara...
،إنما قبل 22 عامًا
was destroyed by a Marine buster call.
موطنك أوهارا أتى عليه نداء دمار البحرية فدكه دكًا
This is my theory:
...أنا
Ohara was destroyed because it discovered that kingdom's existence.
أرجح حدوثه لعلم أوهارا بوجود تلك المملكة...
The Void Century...
...القرن الفارغ
is the history of a conflict between that highly advanced kingdom...
...سُطرت فيه معلومات عن المملكة المزدهرة
and an alliance of twenty kingdoms.
وتاريخ صراعها ضد الممالك العشرين...
Those twenty kingdoms emerged victorious,
الممالك العشرون الذين انتصروا في الحرب
and founded the World Government, creating the world as we know it today.
أسسوا فيما بعد حكومة العالم وأرسوا العالم كما نعرفه اليوم
Then, in order to ensure that the ideals of that kingdom were never passed down,
ولمنع أي إنسان من تبني العقيدة الفكرية لتلك المملكة القديمة
they erased it from history completely.
محوا أثرها من صفحات التاريخ
What...? That's crazy...!
هذا كلامٌ يصعُب تصديقه
H-Huh?! Are you serious?!
أما تقوله حقيقي؟
What a thrilling tale!
!يا لها من حكاية مثيرة
Wait a minute, Vegapunk!
!مهلًا يا ڨيغابانك
If they sounded a buster call on Ohara for that...
،إن كانت أوهارا أُرسل إليها نداء الدمار لذلك
that means the people who learn about it...
...فهل يعقل أن الناس الذين يعلمون عنها
Yeah, they'll be erased.
!أجل، سيُقتلون
Hey! Why did you even tell us?!
!ويلك! ما بالك تحدثنا عن شيء لم نسأل عنه؟
Dammit!
!تبًّا
I heard every word he said!
!لقد سمعت ذلك
I can't unhear it...
...ولأنني سمعت
Time to forget!
!سأنسى
I know nothing!
!لا أعرف شيئًا
I didn't hear it! I don't know it!
!لم أسمع! لا أعرف أي شيء
No thoughts! Just forget!
!لم أسمع! انساه
Calm down a little.
اهدأ قليلًا
I heard nothing! Nothing at all!
ما قلته مجرد فرضية
This is horrible!
!هذا سيئ! لا أريد الموت
However, Nico Robin...
إنما يا نيكو روبين
if Ohara was destroyed for this theory...
،إن كانت أوهارا دُمرت لهذه الفرضية
isn't the government basically admitting it's true?
فألا يعني ذلك أن الحكومة تقر بصحتها؟
Whose side are you on, exactly?
إلى من تدين بالولاء؟
The scholars of Ohara studied precious historical texts to arrive at that theory...
ظل علماء أوهارا يدرسون المعارف القيمة وتوصلوا إلى فرضية
Wouldn't the government tell someone as high up as you?
ألا يخولك منصبك الرفيع أن تطلعك الحكومة على ذلك؟
No, they haven't told me anything.
كلا، لم يخبروني بأي شيء
It's the same for everyone.
ما يزال المبدأ قائمًا
Discussing this would result in my erasure, regardless of my affiliation.
لن تشفع لي تبعيتي إلى الحكومة عن قتلي إن ذكرت الأمر
Then I don't wanna know!
!إذًا لا أريد أن أعرف
This is like torture!
!إن هذا كالتعذيب
Get me outta here!
!غادر المكان
Then how did you learn about the kingdom?!
!فكيف عرفت عن تلك المملكة؟
All the books Ohara collected from across the world... were...
...إن المُؤلْفَات التي جمعتها أوهارا من شتى بقاع العالم قد
The will of Ohara lives on.
إرادة أوهارا باقية
The events of that day threw the world into confusion.
أُصيب العالم بالحيرة يومها
The island of scholars, Ohara, with the most advanced knowledge in the world,
،جزيرة أوهارا الأكاديمية التي تعد منارة المعرفة في العالم
was destroyed in a single day, save for one little girl...
دُمرت بين عشيةٍ وضحاها باستثناء فتاة واحدة
The scholars were labeled as a group of devils...
كانت تهمة أوهارا أنهم علماء أشرار يخططون للإطاحة بحكومة العالم
Several months after the incident...
،وبعد عدة أشهر من الحادثة
I visited Ohara.
زرت أوهارا
I was somewhat acquainted with Professor Clover, an authority on archaeology.
فقد جمعتني معرفة بشيخ علماء الآثار البروفيسور كلوفر
so I wanted to leave flowers.
فأردت تأبينه بالأزهار
You knew him?!
!كنت تعرف البروفيسور كلوفر؟
Yeah.
أجل
He was obsessed with the Void Century...
،كان مهووسًا بالقرن الفارغ
enough to set off on adventures to scour the world for related texts.
فخاض المغامرات في العالم بحثًا عن وثائق حوله
The Marines arrested and jailed him no fewer than ten times...
قبضت عليه البحرية وزُج في السجن عشر مرات
There he is!
!وجدته
It made him the most famous archaeologist in the world.
!وأصبح كلوفر أشهر عالم آثار في العالم
Eventually, word of his exploits drew scholars to Ohara,
في نهاية المطاف، اجتمع العلماء -الذين اتخذوه قدوة- في أوهارا
which became a haven for archaeology.
وأصبحت الجزيرة مركزًا لعلم الآثار
One might say his talent is what caused that tragedy.
فلربما المأساة وقعت نظرًا لنباغته
When I set foot on Ohara,
حين وطئت قدمي أوهارا
the place was in ruins.
وجدتها صارت خرابًا لا عمران فيها
Even the Tree of Knowledge had burned to the ground...
،حتى شجرة المعرفة سويت بالأرض
with everything around it reduced to ash.
وكل شيء أمسى رمادًا محترق
But as I walked deeper into the island,
وحين توغلت في أعماق الجزيرة
I witnessed something astonishing.
رأيت ما لم يخطر على بال
What is all of this?!
!ما هذا؟
A vast amount of books of all kinds...
كُتب كثيرة في شتى المعارف
were submerged in the lake at the center of the island!
مغمورة في مياه بحيرة وسط الجزيرة
I believe that the scholars stood their ground, even as the buster call burned their home,
لربما بقيَ العلماء في الجزيرة المحترقة بنداء الدمار
and died ensuring their legacy would reach the future.
وماتوا حافظين للإرث الذي خلفوه إلى المستقبل
The books that all of those scholars risked their lives for...
،وتلك الكتب التي ضحى الكثير من العلماء لحمايتها
Ignorant Marines wouldn't understand their value, even if they found them.
لن يعرف قيمتها الجنود الجهلاء في حال عثروا عليها
Ohara won.
كان النصر من نصيب أوهارا
When I saw that,
،ولما رأيت ذلك
I couldn't stop the tears from flowing.
لم أتمكن من الكف عن البكاء
Please take Robin!
اعتنِ بروبين
My daughter must escape the island!
هَرِّبْ ابنتي من الجزيرة بأي ثمن
What?!
ماذا؟
No! What about you, Mom?!
كلا، ماذا عنكِ يا أمي؟ ألن تهربي معي؟
Olvia, what are you...?
ماذا ستفعلين يا أوليفيا؟
There's still something that I have to do here, so...
ثمة أمر ما يزال علي فعله
Mom! Don't leave me!
أماه! لا أريد الابتعاد عنكِ
I'll stay here too!
سأبقى هنا أيضًا
Robin...
روبين
As an Oharan scholar, you should understand this well.
أنت باحثة من أوهارا، فستعرفين ما سأقوله
History is the legacy of mankind.
التاريخ ثروة البشرية
Put out the fire!
أخمدوا الحريق
Protect the books!
احموا الكتب
Save as many books as we can!
أنقذوا أكبر عدد ممكن من الكتب
Throw the books out of the library!
ارموا الكتب خارج المكتبة
Ohara doesn't want to expose our history.
ما  كانت أوهارا تنتوي كشف خفايا التاريخ
We only wished to preserve the voices of the past.
فما أردنا إلا سماع أصوات الماضي وحمايتها
Our research ends here...
...هذه نهاية مطاف بحثنا، لكن حتى لو اندثرت أوهارا
we cannot forsake...
!لن نتخلى عن الغد الذي ستعيشون فيه أنتم اليافعين
I don't understand!
لا أفهم
You will... someday.
يومًا ستفهمين
Now...
...هيا
go, Saul!
اذهب يا ساول
Are you sure about this?
هل أنتِ راضية؟
Yes.
أجل
I don't wanna go! I wanna stay with you, Mom!
كلا، سأبقى هنا أنا أيضًا يا أمي
Mom!
!أمي
Live, Robin!
عيشي يا روبين
Hold your head high, Robin!
!افخري يا روبين
Your mom is honorable!
!فإن أمكِ كانت ذات عزة
Someday, pass down this island's history, Robin!
دوني تاريخ هذه الجزيرة ذات يوم يا روبين
Ohara fought against the world!
استبسلت أوهارا ضد العالم
What's the matter, Robin?
ما الأمر يا آنسة روبين؟
Hey! How dare you make Robin cry, you bucket head!
مهلًا! ما بك تُبكي روبين يا أبا خوذة؟
That's it, Vegapunk!
لن أسامحك يا ڨيغابانك، سأركلك
Get these shoes off me so I can kick your ass!
انزع عني هذا الحذاء أيها الوغد
You're so insensitive, Vega!
!أنت غير مراعٍ لمشاعر الآخرين
Get 'em off!
هذا صحيح
Pay attention, bucket head!
انظر إلي يا أبا خوذة
Vegapunk.
ڨيغابانك
It's like you thought.
،كما خمنت تمامًا
Ohara uncovered the existence of that kingdom.
كشفت أوهارا عن وجود المملكة
I see. Then it is true.
فهمت، إذًا هذه حقيقة
Where are the books from the lake now?
تلك الكتب التي كانت في البحيرة، أين هي؟
I wanted to bring them back to Punk Hazard,
أنا أردت العودة بها إلى بانك هازارد
but I couldn't risk the higher-ups hearing about it.
ولكن إن عرف كبار المسؤولين ذلك، فسينتهي كل شيء
To tell you the truth...
...إنما حينها
I met some people that day.
قابلت أولئك الرجال
Who'd be here in ruins like these?
من هؤلاء؟ وماذا يفعلون هنا؟
Pull it up!
!اسحب
Giants?!
!عمالقة؟
What are they up to?
لمَ يفعلون ذلك؟
Are they aware of the value of these books?!
!هل يعلمون قيمة تلك الكتب؟
The books...
...الكتب
What are they gonna do with them?!
ماذا سيفعلون بهم؟
That head of yours...
كما هي عادتك
It's as big as ever. I'd recognize it anywhere.
رأسك مميز، تعرفت عليه فورًا
It's been a while, Vegapunk.
لم أرك منذ زمن يا فيغابانك
Dragon?!
!دراغون
Your head got bigger again.
ازداد رأسك حجمًا مرة أخرى
Never mind that!
دعك من هذا
Why are you here?!
ما الذي أتى بك إلى هنا؟
That's my question, Vegapunk.
هذا سؤالي لك أيضًا يا فيغابانك
I knew old man Clover.
كنت أعرف العجوز كلوفر
Oh? You, too?
ما هذا؟ أنت أيضًا؟
Well...
...حسنًا
he used to be a hooligan adventuring all over the place.
فقد اعتاد الترحال حول العالم
That nonsense about him trying to destroy the world...
...وأما مزاعم محاولته تخريب العالم
is poppycock and propaganda!
فهي حملة تضليل سخيفة
Yeah.
أجل
Are you wondering what they're doing?
هل شغلتك تصرفات أولئك العمالقة؟
I can't let them steal those valuable books!
!لا يجدر أن أدعهم يأخذون تلك الكتب القيمة
They're not bandits.
إنهم ليسوا نباشين، فقد تأكدت من نواياهم سلفًا
What?
ماذا؟
They came from Elbaph.
جاؤوا من إلباف
They know the value of the books.
ويعرفون قيمة الكتب
Their captain is a strange man with bandages all over his body...
قبطانهم رجلٌ به غرابة تغطي جسده الضمادات
He said, "The Oharans saved their legacy by sacrificing their lives,
قال إن شعب أوهارا افتدوا تراثهم بأرواحهم
and I won't let it be erased from history."
ولن يسمح أن يمحى من التاريخ
It's a good thing that you government people...
وكونك لم تعلم أنت ولا رؤسائك في حكومة العالم عنها
didn't find and destroy the books first.
حفظ الكتب من محاولة إتلافها
Hey, wait!
...على رسلك! لم أكن لأفعل هذا
I thought it was a joke!
ظننت في الأمر ابتذالًا
I couldn't believe you'd actually become a government lapdog.
فمن غير المعقول أن تصبح كلبًا وفيًا للحكومة
And after turning down our invitation to join the Freedom Fighters, too...
بعد أن رفضت الانضمام إلى جيش الحرية معنا
Don't be stupid!
كفى بك سخافة
Even with my talent and intellect,
،حتى مع حكمتي ومهاراتي
what could I create in a poorly funded outfit like yours?!
كيف كنت لأنجح في جيش تنقصه الموارد كجيشك؟
I get it.
أتفهم هذا
You're as blunt as ever.
لا تنطق إلا بصريح الكلام كعادتك
The World Government is an enormous organization.
حكومة العالم منظمة ضخمة
The Marines, especially, are full of reasonable people.
لكل الجدران آذاني وجدران البحرية كُثر
Don't lose sight of the goal, Dragon.
لا تَحِدْ عن هدفك يا دراغون
I know, but...
...إني بذلك عليم
this incident really shook me.
هذه الحادثة أضجت مضجعي
A group of harmless scholars were violently eradicated...
،والعلماء المغلوبين على أمرهم الذين شككوا في معقولية الثوابت
simply for questioning that absurd "law"!
كُسرت أنوفهم بالقوة الغاشمة
But I'm going to raise an army that can fight back!
سأشيد جيشًا يمكنه القتال
I thought you despised war!
!لكنك تحتقر الحروب
Just you wait, Vegapunk.
ارتقب يا فيغابانك
I'm going to change the world!
!أنا سأغير العالم
I won't let Clover's death...
،موت كلوفر
or the will of Ohara go to waste!
وإرداة أوهارا، لن يذهبا سدى
Later that year, Dragon teamed up with...
...تعاون دراغون في وقتٍ لاحق ذلك العام مع
Emporio Ivankov...
...إمبوريو إيفانكوف
and Bartholomew Kuma...
...وبارثلوميو كوما
to create the Revolutionary Army...
لهز جنبات العالم...
that now shakes the world!
بالجيش الثوري الذين وضعوا حجر أساسه
Luffy's dad is so ambitious!
والد لوفي شغوفٌ بأفكاره
Wait just a second! Did you say Elbaph?!
!مهلًا! هل ذكرت إلباف توًّا؟
I didn't know Dragon and Professor Clover knew each other...!
لم أعلم أن السيد دراغون والبروفيسور كلوفر يعرفان بعضهما
That bastard Iva was a founding member of the Revolutionary Army?
إيفا اللعين! لم أعلم أنه أحد الأعضاء المؤسسين للجيش الثوري
I feel like my brain's gonna explode!
يكاد عقلي ينفجر
Why did Kuma help us?!
لماذا ساعدنا كوما؟
Why did you modify him, Vegapunk?!
لماذا عدلت على جسد كوما؟
While it's true the government must not find Ohara's books...
كان يجدر أن تبقى كتب أوهارا مخبأة عن أنظار الحكومة بلا ريب
I secretly went to Elbaph anyway for reasons of my own.
غير أني زرت إلباف سرًا لحاجةٍ في نفسي
I read every document there.
وقرأت جميع الوثائق
So...
،ما يعني
the mystery of the world that Ohara unraveled...
سر العالم الذي كشفته أوهارا
lives on in my brain...
محفور في عقلي وهو استقصاء بحثي أعمل عليه
Can I ask you one thing?
هل يمكنني سؤالك شيئًا؟
That giant captain...
...اسم قبطان العمالقة
Saul, wasn't it?
ساول، أليس كذلك؟...
He's in hiding now.
إنه مختبئ حاليًا
I must keep it a secret from everyone.
وهذا سرٌ أحفظه عن الجميع
Thank you, Vegapunk...
شكرًا يا فيغابانك
for not allowing Ohara's struggle to be for nothing.
فمعركة شعب أوهارا لم تذهب سدى
I'm simply well versed in all areas of study.
أنا على دراية حسنة بجميع فروع المعرفة
It's the way of a true scholar.
أليس تلك سمة العلامة؟
The shoes are moving on their own!
تتحرك الأحذية من تلقاء نفسها
I can't release you yet. You'll have to come with me.
لا أستطيع إطلاق سراحكم! ولكن اتبعوني
There's something I want to show you.
فثمة ما أريد أن أريكم إياه
Hey! There's no cockpit on this thing, Chopper.
اسمع! لا توجد قمرة قيادة لهذا الشيء يا تشوبر
I got it! Maybe this robot...
...فهمت، لربما هذا الآلي
moves on its own!
!من الأنواع ذاتية القيادة...
Maybe it'll react if we say something to it!
!ربما سيبدي ردة فعل إن وجهنا أمرًا له
Like... Like...
...إذًا... إذًا
Move! Move, robot!
!تحرك! تحرك يا آلي
It didn't work...
لم ينجح
I wonder what the magic word is...
ما هي العبارة المناسبة يا ترى؟
No! It must have a name!
!لا! لا بد أن له اسم
We should call it out!
!فلنناده بذلك
Move, Robonosuke!
!تحرك يا آلينوسكي
Robo King!
!الآلي الملك
Jeez...
بئسًا! أأنتما طفلان؟
That obviously won't work.
لن تتمكنا من تحريكه هكذا
Are you okay?
هل أنت بخير؟
Yeah...
بلى
What was that?! Did the robot explode?!
ما كان هذا؟ هل انفجر الآلي؟
No, it wasn't an explosion.
كلا، لم يكن انفجارًا
Then what just happened?!
ماذا حدث إذًا؟
Hey!
لو سمحتم
Help me-quasar!
ساعدوني-كويزار
"Quasar"?
كويزار؟
Oh no!
!مشكلة! فشل آخر
Somebody, help me-quasar!
فليساعدني أحد-كويزار
Maybe I warped space-time when I teleported!
!لربما تشوه الزمكان حال انتقالي آنيًا
Was that old man there before?
هل كان هذا العم هناك من قبل؟
I don't think so.
لا أظن
I'm sinking! Hey!
إني أغرق، ساعدوني
My body's sinking!
!جسدي يغرق
Somebody!
!أحدٌ ما
I don't know what's going on.
لا أعرف ما يحدث! هل تحتاج مساعدة يا عم؟
Help me-quasar!
ساعدوني-كويزار
What the...?
ما هذا؟ أنت مثل كينيمون يا هذا
Hurry up!
!أسرع
I'll get you out!
سأُخرجك حالًا
Thanks!
!المعذرة
I knew it!
إنه هو فعلًا
Thank you!
!شكرًا
By the way, you're...
...بالمناسبة، ألست
Dragon's son, right?
ابن دراغون؟...
I knew you were here.
!علمت بمجيئك، وهذا سرني
And you must be...
...أيضًا
Bonney!
!بوني جاءت...
You're all grown up!
!لقد كبرتِ
Vegapunk!
!ڨيغابانك
I'm glad to see you doing well!
!أنا سعيد لرؤيتكِ بخير
Old man, are you floating?!
هل تطفو أيها العم؟
You're wearing them, too.
ألا ترتدي مثلها؟
Those dom shoes have a hover function!
!تتميز أحذية التحكم هذه بخاصية الحومان
What?! A hover function?!
!ماذا؟ خاصية الحومان
How do we use it?!
كيف نستخدمها؟
First, press the button on the side...
أولًا، اضغطوا على الزر الجانبي
Oh, this one.
هذا الزر
And this lever!
وبعده الرافعة
Push it down!
!ادفعوها إلى الأسفل على آخرها
Like this?!
!هكذا؟
That's it!
!تمامًا
We flew too high!
!طفونا أكثر من اللازم
Help me-quasar!
ساعدوني-كويزار